{
  "title": "General_Aptitude-_CSE - Verbal_Ability_–_CSE — Slot 5 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Verbal_Ability_–_CSE — Slot 5",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Most experts feel that in spite of possessing all the technical skills required to be a batsman of the highest order, he is unlikely to be so due to lack of requisite temperament. He was guilty of throwing away his wicket several time after working hard to lay a strong foundation. His critics pointed out that until he addressed his problem, success at the highest level will continue to elude him. <br>Which of the statement(s) below is/are logically valid and can be inferred from the above passage?\n<br><br>i.   He was already a successful batsman at the highest level.\n<br>ii.  He was to improve his temperament in order to become a great batsman.\n<br>iii. He failed to make many of his good starts count.\n<br>iv.  Improving his technical skills will guarantee success. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>iii and iv</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>ii and iii</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>i, ii and iii</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>ii only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>ii and iii</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"#a_list\" target=\"_blank&quot;\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Alexander turned his attention towards India, since he had conquered Persia.\n<br><br>\nWhich one of the statements below is logically valid and can be inferred from the above sentence? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Alexander would not have turned his attention towards India had he not conquered Persia.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Alexander was not ready to rest on his laurels, and wanted to march to India.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Alexander was not completely in control of his army and could command it to move towards India.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Since Alexander's kingdom extended to Indian borders after the conquest of Persia, he was keen to move further.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Alexander would not have turned his attention towards India had he not conquered Persia.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8306/gate-cse-2015-set-3-question-ga-6#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Select the pair of best expresses a relationship similar to that expressed in the pair:\n<br><br>\nChildren : Pediatrician <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Adult : Orthopaedist</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Females : Gynaecologist</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Kidney : Nephrologist</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Skin : Dermatologist</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Females : Gynaecologist</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8302/gate-cse-2015-set-3-question-ga-4#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Extreme focus on syllabus and studying for tests has become such a dominant concern of Indian student that they close their minds to anything ___________ to the requirements of the exam. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>related</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>extraneous</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>outside</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>useful</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>extraneous</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8301/gate-cse-2015-set-3-question-ga-3#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>The Tamil version of __________ John Abraham-starrer Madras Cafe __________ cleared by the Censor Board with no cuts last week, but the film's distributor _______ no takers among the exhibitors for a release in Tamilnadu _______ this Friday. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Mr., was, found, on</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>a, was, found, at</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>the, was, found, on</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>a, being, find at</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>the, was, found, on</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8300/gate-cse-2015-set-3-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>If ROAD is written as URDG, then SWANshould be written as: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>VXDQ</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>VZDQ</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>VZDP</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>UXDQ</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>VZDQ</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8298/gate-cse-2015-set-3-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Out of the following 4 sentences, select the most suitable sentence with respect to grammar and usage: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Since the report lacked needed information, it was of no use to them.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The report was useless to them because there were no needed information in it.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Since the report did not contain the needed information, it was not real useful to them.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Since the report lacked needed information, it would not had been useful to them.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Since the report lacked needed information, it was of no use to them.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8041/gate-cse-2015-set-2-question-ga-10#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>A generic term that includes various items of clothing such as a skirt, a pair of trousers and a shirt is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>fabric</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>textile</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>fiber</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>apparel</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>apparel</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8032/gate-cse-2015-set-2-question-ga-4#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Choose the statement where underlined word is used correctly. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The industrialist had a \\(\\underline{ \\text{personnel }}\\) jet.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I write my experience in my \\(\\underline{ \\text{personnel }}\\) diary.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>All \\(\\underline{ \\text{personnel} }\\) are being given the day off.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Being religious is a  \\(\\underline{ \\text{personnel} }\\) aspect.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>All \\(\\underline{ \\text{personnel} }\\) are being given the day off.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8029/gate-cse-2015-set-2-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>We __________ our friends's birthday and we _________ how to make it up to him. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>completely forgot --- don't just know</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>forgot completely ---don't just know</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>completely forgot --- just don't know</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>forgot completely --- just don't know</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>completely forgot --- just don't know</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8028/gate-cse-2015-set-2-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>The given statement is followed by some courses of action. Assuming the statement to be true, decide the correct option.\n<br><br>\nStatement:\n<br>\nThere has been a significant drop in the water level in the lakes supplying water to the city.\n<br><br>\nCourse of action:\n<br>\nI.   The water supply authority should impose a partial cut in supply to tackle the situation.\n<br>II.  The government should appeal to all the residents through mass media for minimal use of water.\n<br>III. The government should ban the water supply in lower areas. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Statements I and II follow.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Statements I and III follow.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Statements II and III follow.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>All the statements follow.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Statements I and II follow.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8012/gate-cse-2015-set-1-question-ga-8#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Select the alternative meaning of the underlined part of the sentence.\n<br>\nThe chain snatchers \\(\\underline{\\text{took to their heels}}\\) when the police party arrived. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Took shelter in a thick jungle</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Open indiscriminate fire</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Took to flight</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Unconditionally surrendered</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Took to flight</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8011/gate-cse-2015-set-1-question-ga-7#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following combinations is incorrect? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Acquiescence - Submission</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Wheedle - Roundabout</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Flippancy - Lightness</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Profligate - Extravagant</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Wheedle - Roundabout</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8008/gate-cse-2015-set-1-question-ga-5#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following options is the closest in meaning of the sentence below?\n<br><br>\nShe enjoyed herself immensely at the party. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>She had a terrible time at the party</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>She had a horrible time at the party</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>She had a terrific time at the party</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>She had a terrifying time at the party</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>She had a terrific time at the party</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8003/gate-cse-2015-set-1-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Didn't you buy ____ when you went shopping? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>any paper</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>much paper</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>no paper</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>a few paper</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>any paper</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/7995/gate-cse-2015-set-1-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}